if you've been hearing about Kafka but
you don't understand what it is and why
all the hype let me clarify it using
real life examples that will make
everything finally click for you imagine
we're building an e-commerce application
called stream store and we have some
microservices handling payments orders
inventory and so on and when something
happens in our application like customer
places an order it's like dominoes where
a chain reaction of updates and events
by other services get triggered like
stock needs to be updated in the
database now that we sold some of it a
notification or confirmation email needs
to be sent to the customer an invoice
needs to be generated with the right
sales tax and sent per email to the
customer um maybe revenue and sales data
needs to be updated on our sales
dashboard and so on now we are a small
startup so we are starting with the
simplest straightforward microservices
architecture where the microservices
just call each other like the order
service would say hey all you guys we
just closed an order go update your
stuff accordingly and it all worked
great at first but suddenly we become a
hit and people are loving our store or
we just announced Black Friday sales and
our store is getting hundreds of
thousands of customers which is amazing
but suddenly our application starts
crashing everything is slowing down
users are sitting in front of loading
screens because our architecture cannot
handle this load we get in panic because
we are losing cells every minute our
architecture that looked pretty clean
and straightforward on the Whiteboard
becomes a nightmare so here is what's
happening in the background first of all
we have what's called tight coupling
between the services which means when
the payment service goes down for
example because some API in the
background isn't responsive or the
service itself just crashes under load
and when that happens our entire order
process freezes we have synchronous
communication so each order feels like a
game of dominoes one slow service and
everything backs up and as I said during
peak times customers are literally
staring at loading screens and we also
have lots of single points of failure
which means a 10-minute inventory
service outage meant 2 hours of order
backlogs and countless lost sales and we
are also losing a lot of analytics data
when the analytics service goes down for
an hour we're losing important Black
Friday sales data after another hectic
and chaotic week we thought what if we
redesign the system so that the orders
flow through the system like items on a
conveyor belt instead of our current
game of hot potato and instead of apps
calling each other directly and waiting
for reply we remove that tide coupling
we basically make space between them and
introduce a tool that sits in the middle
and acts as a broker think of it as post
office when you order something online
the sellers don't come knocking on your
door to deliver package themselves
they hand it over to the post office or
some middleman to deliver your package
or if you are returning your purchase or
sending a package to someone you don't
fly to their place to give them the
package in person post office has this
infrastructure and handles the
processing so Kafka is like the mail
delivery service or post office which
sits in the middle so now the order
service goes to Kafka and hands over a
package called event that says
hey order was made for this customer for
these products and here are all the
details please make this information
available for anyone who needs it to
update and do stuff in the background
bye and it just basically goes back and
continues its work and an event looks
like this with very simple structure
with key value pair and metadata
information so the order service does
not need to wait there to make sure that
the others actually got the information
it can trust this broker that it will be
delivered to the right services and all
this will happen in the background like
in the post office you just drop off
your package and go home you don't wait
there sitting and checking whether they
actually ship the package or not because
you know that will take care of the rest
and the order service that gives that
information to Kafka or basically a
service that produces this event and
hands it over to kfka is called a
producer because it produces events and
in code this is how it would look like
using Kafka producer API so in
JavaScript or Java code you basically
use that API to create an event and give
it to CFA now where does this
information or these events get saved
when producers of those events give them
to Kafka because we have bunch of other
services like inventory payment and so
on that also produce certain events and
hand it over to kka with all the
information that other services may need
when inventory gets updated or the
payment service says that the payment
just failed and so on so do all these
events from different producers get
dumped into a giant bucket in Kafka or
are they organized somehow if we had one
big bucket handling all the rights and
reads it will not be very performant
right it's like having one single queue
in the post office so if weather sending
a letter or package or picking up your
delivery everyone would be standing in
the same queue instead imagine that post
office will add sections with their own
cues like a section for letters another
one for large packages and so on so
Kafka has what's called topics to group
the same type of events so for example
order service will write events to
orders topic the payments service May
update payments topic and so on now how
do those topics get created or who
defines them well just like you define a
SQL schema for your database based on
what your application needs and what
objects you have you as an engineer
decide how to group these events in
Kafka in what topics so now that the
order service added an event to the
order topic what happens next that event
May trigger other actions like updating
stock in the database because we just
sold something or sending notification
to customer or updating invoice and
sales status plus what other topics may
exist that would need an event data
entry as a result of an order which will
in turn trigger other actions so how
does all that get handled well on the
other side of events we have consumers
basic basically microservices who are
subscribed to these different topics and
whenever a new event happens and gets
added to this topic all consumers who
are subscribed get notified by Kafka and
they then do their stuff in this case we
have three microservices that subscribe
to the order event notification service
we'll see that a new order event was
added which means a order was placed in
our application
and based on the payload of that event
it will send a confirmation email to the
customer and maybe a purchase
notification to your email then an
inventory service May update the
database by updating the stocks of every
product that was sold in that order and
maybe in addition to that database
update we'll generate a new event and
write it into an inventory topic and
then finally the payment service May
generate invoice and send it to the user
now I hope you're learning a lot and the
topic of Kafka is becoming clear for you
it takes us on average two or 3 weeks to
produce one such video so if you find it
valuable we would appreciate if you left
your feedback or liked the video and
we'd be happy to have you as our
subscriber as well now you may be asking
is kfka a replacement of a database
somehow since we are SA saving all these
data as events and basically updating
the status of things so is it kind of a
new way of saving things a simple answer
is no it's not a replacement database
let's explain by following our story so
when the inventory service updates the
stock for each product in the database
why does it produce an event and write
it to the inventory topic what kind of
event that may be and why would we have
it in addition to the dat in the
database well that's another use case of
kfka where one event basically creates
this chain reaction of events when
multiple things need to happen as a
result of one event happening which we
saw an example you may have another
service that is subscribed to the
inventory topic and calculates whether
any of the products just gone below the
inventory threshold and produce a low
inventory alert which maybe as a chain
reaction will trigger another service
that may trigger an inventory restock
service that will order more inventory
of that specific product another very
important use case of Kafka is realtime
analytics for example again when sales
happen in your application you may have
a sales dashboard where your service is
updating real time sales numbers and
other such use case is driver location
updates in an application like uber
where the driver location
changes get sent constantly to the
application which then updates the UI of
the user to display those changes and
for all these use cases Kafka actually
uses what's called Stream apis So on one
side you have these regular consumers
that will process one event at a time
for example a notification service that
will read an order event and based on
that we'll send an email or notification
to the customer streams on the other
hand will process continuous flow of
data with aggregations and joints and so
on in order to do realtime processing
and analytics on them so for example low
inventory validations to check
constantly with every event and do the
calculation to see whether inventory
just dropped below the threshold or get
the location changes from the drivers so
this analytic services will stream the
events Contin ly doing various analytics
and calculations on them and in code you
would have a streams API that will read
the orders and do all these kinds of
calculations on them now as I mentioned
these are streams of constant data saved
as events in kfka because you have an
application like uber with millions of
users and tens of thousands of drivers
with their locations getting updated
constantly that's a lot of data and
events that are being produced right and
all consumers need to read from it so
millions of writes and reads in
different Kafka topics which can of
course affect performance so we need to
scale and that's where kafka's partition
concept comes in which is kind of a core
of kafka's ability to scale and become
really performant so partitions are
basically what make processing large
amounts of data easy to handle and
process without compromising the
performance so how does it work exactly
with our post office example remember we
edit sections for letters large packages
small packages and so on partitions are
like adding more workers per section to
help out so suddenly Before Christmas
the letters section get overloaded
because everyone's sending letters to
centa well sadly that doesn't happen but
if it did we would add more workers in
that section but not just randomly
instead you say an processes letters
going to Europe Steve handle's letters
to us Jay handle's ones to Asia and so
on same way in Kafka in the orders topic
you may create EU orders partition us
orders Asia orders and so on and again
you would decide how to partition your
topic as part of your schema design now
let's think about the consumer side
let's say suddenly millions of orders
are coming in and we said we can can
scale this with partitions so producers
can write into multiple partitions at
the same time but what about the
consumers how can they consume so much
data at once because even if you have
partitions you'll have one consumer
let's say inventory service trying to
process all the events that it's
subscribed to which is like all the
parcels going to one person recipient
like thousands of letters going to Santa
those post office workers are being
super quick and are delivering them to
the recipient but he's getting buried
under the pile but we need some people
helping him sort through this and that's
where consumer groups come in so when
you start additional instances of that
microservice like replicas in kubernetes
they can all consume from CFA partitions
and process events faster in parallel
now how does Kafka know which consumers
form a group and how to divide and which
ones Belong Together simple they are
grouped by the group ID attribute when
they register as consumers with kfka so
replicas of the same application will
have the same group IDs and will
automatically be grouped together and
when you start replicas Kafka
distributes the load automatically by
assigning partitions to Consumers so
kfka says oh we have a new helper now
you can process this pile of letters
here and when that helper stops working
it will take the pile and give it to
another active one now the final
question is where is this data
physically saved data in topics is saved
on CFA servers called Brokers and you
can think of each broker like a post
office branch that stores the actual
messages on disk handles requests from
producers and consumers and replicates
the data for fault tolerance even if
something happens with the dis the data
is stored somewhere else as a backup and
this is actually what makes Kafka
different from standard message Brokers
so while regular message cues would
delete messages after consumption so as
soon as consumers see that message and
do something with it that message is
gone kavka however persists every event
or message as long as you need and you
can configure how long you want to store
them with a retention policy so think of
it like our post office keeping a log of
all package deliveries but not just for
record keeping but for analyzing
patterns and improving service so that
unique feature of kfka for real-time
data processing and general analytics
means that kfka needs to store those
events long-term so the consumers can
read those events anytime they want even
multi multiple times if they need to and
as I said this capability to process
streams of data in real time while
keeping the original data for later
analysis is what really differentiates
Kafka from simple message Brokers so
that's the main difference and for even
clearer comparison think of this as
difference between watching Netflix and
watching TV Netflix is on demand so
consumers or people who are the viewers
can decide themselves what they want to
watch when they want to watch it and at
what pace so they can stop and pause
anytime and continue whenever they want
or they can replay or start from the
beginning with TV you have predefined
programs and people who want to view
those programs need to tune in at
specific time to watch specific stuff so
everyone watches the same thing at the
same time at the same Pace you can't
pause and continue later if you miss a
movie or show you just miss it and it's
not automatically saved to watch later
and that's exactly the difference
between Kafka architecture versus other
traditional message Brokers and finally
Kafka needs a way to keep track of which
Brokers are alive elect leaders to
coordinate manage all the configuration
and traditionally Kafka used an external
tool called zookeeper for this type of
coordination so it was like a central
management for all the Kafka Brokers
however important to note that the newer
versions of Kafka from version 3.0
introduced K raft or Kafka raft which
removes the need for zookeeper as this
external dependency with centralized
control by building that coordination
directly into Kafka now I hope I made
Kafka finally clear for you share it
with one colleague who you think will
benefit from it and with that thanks for
watching and see you in the next video